Brian's Song is a drama, tv movie film directed by Buzz Kulik.
Based on the real-life relationship between teammates Brian Piccolo and Gale Sayers
and the bond established when Piccolo discovers that he is dying.
Brian Piccolo, played by James Caan.
Gale Sayers, played by Billy Dee Williams.
Coach Halas, played by Jack Warden.
J.C. Caroline, played by Bernie Casey.
Joy Piccolo, played by Shelley Fabares.
Ed McCaskey, played by David Huddleston.
Brian's Song is a 1971 ABC Movie of the Week that recounts the life of Brian Piccolo (James Caan), a Chicago Bears football
player stricken with terminal cancer, focusing on his friendship with teammate Gale Sayers (Billy Dee Williams).
Piccolo's and Sayers's sharply differing temperaments and racial backgrounds made them unlikely to become friends but
they did, becoming the first interracial roommates in the history of the National Football League.
The film chronicles the evolution of their friendship,
ending with Piccolo's death in 1970.
The production was such a success on ABC that it was later shown in theaters by Columbia Pictures
with a major premiere in Chicago; however, it was soon withdrawn for lack of business.
Critics have called the movie one of the finest television movies ever made.
A 2005 readers' poll taken by Entertainment Weekly ranked Brian's
Song seventh in its list of the top "guy-cry" films.
The movie is based on Sayers's account of his friendship with Piccolo and coping
with Piccolo's illness in Sayers's 1970 autobiography, I Am Third.
The film was written by William Blinn, whose script one Dallas television critic called "highly restrained, steering clear of
any overt sentimentality [yet conveying] the genuine affection the two men felt so deeply for each other."
The film explores themes of friendship, sports,
american football, terminal illness, cancer.
The tone is emotional.